<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on data Blog = Blog { me :: Programmer, posts :: [Opinion] }</title>
    <link>https://asthasr.github.io/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on data Blog = Blog { me :: Programmer, posts :: [Opinion] }</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2024 09:21:48 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://asthasr.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Building Bridges</title>
      <link>https://asthasr.github.io/posts/building-bridges/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2024 09:21:48 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://asthasr.github.io/posts/building-bridges/</guid>
      <description>Programming is neither an art nor a science, as I wrote in Orthodoxy, but we have an advantage over other crafts in that we can experiment cheaply and our material is our own creativity, like writers rather than sculptors. Where a sculptor working in wood can never escape the possibility of an unexpected knot or flaw in the grain, we&amp;rsquo;re able to tie our &amp;ldquo;material&amp;rdquo; directly to proven theory and to physical reality.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orthodoxy</title>
      <link>https://asthasr.github.io/posts/orthodoxy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Nov 2024 09:16:51 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://asthasr.github.io/posts/orthodoxy/</guid>
      <description>Programming is neither a science nor an art. Science proceeds from hypothesis through test to confirmation, and art is as much about the means of expression as it is about its themes. Software, by contrast, is written to solve a problem that&amp;rsquo;s fundamentally more important than the means of its solution. Often that solution has existed since ancient times and simply needs to be encoded as an algorithm that works in the particular environment of the software&amp;rsquo;s patron.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Information Curation for the Programmer</title>
      <link>https://asthasr.github.io/posts/curation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Oct 2024 20:05:57 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://asthasr.github.io/posts/curation/</guid>
      <description>I ended the last post, &amp;ldquo;Generative AI and the Programmer,&amp;rdquo; on a note that&amp;rsquo;s a Rorschach test for your own outlook on life: the fate of the technology industry relies on the ability of our practitioners to curate and digest information. My own outlook is frankly pessimistic. Most of us have ignored our own history and, worse, the broad range of &amp;ldquo;liberal arts,&amp;rdquo; producing professionals uniquely and ironically unsuited to critically engaging with the informational ecosystems that we have been instrumental in building.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generative AI and the Programmer</title>
      <link>https://asthasr.github.io/posts/generative-ai/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://asthasr.github.io/posts/generative-ai/</guid>
      <description>If you&amp;rsquo;re one of my loyal readers(?), you&amp;rsquo;ve probably noticed that I don&amp;rsquo;t write much anymore. It&amp;rsquo;s a common fate for blogs, but in this case I can point to a specific cause that has impacted my willingness to write: large language models (LLMs). Since ChatGPT burst onto the scene and illustrated the capabilities of generative AI, I&amp;rsquo;ve found it impossible to finish drafts because I hesitate to throw more information into the datavore.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding the Strategy Pattern</title>
      <link>https://asthasr.github.io/posts/understanding-strategy-pattern/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Apr 2022 08:47:10 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://asthasr.github.io/posts/understanding-strategy-pattern/</guid>
      <description>Conditionals (if, switch, and match statements) are usually the first programmers reach for when we need to vary the execution of a function. They&amp;rsquo;re easy to understand and convenient to use, as long as the variations are simple. As software grows, though, extensibility and comprehensibility begin to require that we create ways to &amp;ldquo;hook&amp;rdquo; new functionality into our functions. The strategy pattern offers a method to accomplish that:&#xA;Define a family of algorithms, encapsulate each one, and make them interchangeable.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Blockchains Work</title>
      <link>https://asthasr.github.io/posts/how-blockchains-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Mar 2021 10:49:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://asthasr.github.io/posts/how-blockchains-work/</guid>
      <description>Chances are, you know what Bitcoin is. After all, it&amp;rsquo;s valued at over $47,000 per Bitcoin right now. This post isn&amp;rsquo;t about the business side of things, though, or the BTC speculative bubble. I want to explain how it works.1&#xA;Foundations: Hashes and Ledgers First, a hash algorithm is a way to convert a given string into an unpredictable string of a fixed length, called a digest.&#xA;Here&amp;rsquo;s a small Python program to demonstrate:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Abstraction is Okay, Magic is Not</title>
      <link>https://asthasr.github.io/posts/abstraction-is-okay/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Feb 2021 20:47:38 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://asthasr.github.io/posts/abstraction-is-okay/</guid>
      <description>You encounter a crusty old-timer who tells you how great programming used to be: the computer just did what you told it. Languages were simple and easy to understand. In awe, you ask: &amp;ldquo;Did you write FORTRAN? or assembly?&amp;rdquo; The old-timer laughs: he&amp;rsquo;s not that old. He started with C!&#xA;It&amp;rsquo;s common to think of C and other &amp;ldquo;old&amp;rdquo; languages as being &amp;ldquo;close to the machine,&amp;rdquo; but that&amp;rsquo;s because the Unix abstractions have become so ubiquitous that we no longer think of them as abstractions.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rust Needs Metaphors, Part 2: Traits</title>
      <link>https://asthasr.github.io/posts/rust-needs-metaphors-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Oct 2020 06:29:48 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://asthasr.github.io/posts/rust-needs-metaphors-2/</guid>
      <description>When I began learning Haskell, typeclasses were confusing to me: at first, because I didn&amp;rsquo;t fully understand why they were needed, and later, because I didn&amp;rsquo;t understand the advantages they offered over Java&amp;rsquo;s interfaces. If you&amp;rsquo;re new to Rust but haven&amp;rsquo;t used Haskell before, you&amp;rsquo;ll likely be in the same boat, but moreso; traits are pervasive in the ecosystem.&#xA;At heart, traits are very similar to interfaces in Java or C♯.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rust Needs Metaphors, Part 1: Lifetimes</title>
      <link>https://asthasr.github.io/posts/rust-needs-metaphors-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://asthasr.github.io/posts/rust-needs-metaphors-1/</guid>
      <description>I recently had a conversation with a friend who said: &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t trust most of what I hear about Rust, because it sounds like agitprop from the Rust Evangelism Strike Force, but people like you whom I trust and respect seem to like it. Can you help me understand why?&amp;rdquo;&#xA;I tried to. I said things that make sense, in the abstract: it offers a very powerful type system, it allows me to feel more confident about my code in surprising ways, and so on.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Under the Rug: Hidden (but Essential) Complexity</title>
      <link>https://asthasr.github.io/posts/under-the-rug/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Apr 2020 08:16:06 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://asthasr.github.io/posts/under-the-rug/</guid>
      <description>I don&amp;rsquo;t like docopt. That makes me an outlier; most people I&amp;rsquo;ve talked to seem to think it makes command-line applications &amp;ldquo;easy.&amp;rdquo; They like its premise that, by writing documentation, you&amp;rsquo;re writing code. When you make a command-line application with docopt, you&amp;rsquo;ve automatically got the help text written and the module documented properly, right? Why bother with something verbose and object-oriented like argparse?&#xA;My objection is that you aren&amp;rsquo;t writing code, but you&amp;rsquo;re also not writing documentation, despite the name of the package.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Loops and Recursion</title>
      <link>https://asthasr.github.io/posts/loops-and-recursion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Dec 2019 08:27:13 +0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://asthasr.github.io/posts/loops-and-recursion/</guid>
      <description>Recursion was a concept that took me a long time to understand. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t until years after I&amp;rsquo;d started programming that I felt I really understood it, and it wasn&amp;rsquo;t until years after that that I felt confident reaching for it as a tool. Like almost everyone, the first way that I learned to think of iteration was with loops. If you wanted to add something together, for example, you would create a &amp;ldquo;bookkeeping&amp;rdquo; variable and modify it inside the loop.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The M-Word: The Culture of Programming</title>
      <link>https://asthasr.github.io/posts/the-m-word/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2019 15:46:58 +0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://asthasr.github.io/posts/the-m-word/</guid>
      <description>In addition to it begin useful, it is also cursed and the curse of the monad is that once you get the epiphany, once you understand&amp;mdash;&amp;ldquo;Oh, that&amp;rsquo;s what it is!&amp;rdquo;&amp;mdash;you lose the ability to explain it to anybody. &amp;mdash; Doug Crockford.&#xA;I had a problem, once. I was working on a Rails application which generated integration files to be consumed by external partners. They were generated every night in a dozen formats and shipped around the Internet to populate sites you&amp;rsquo;ve probably used.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mind the Gaps</title>
      <link>https://asthasr.github.io/posts/mind-the-gaps/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://asthasr.github.io/posts/mind-the-gaps/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;If you truly accumulate effort for a long time, then you will advance.&amp;rdquo; Xunzi.&#xA;It&amp;rsquo;s no secret that many programmers are self-taught. Some of us, myself included, lack formal credentials related to computer science. I&amp;rsquo;ve worked with good programmers who didn&amp;rsquo;t graduate high school. It&amp;rsquo;s a strange profession, with the skills often acquired simply as a side effect of tinkering. You don&amp;rsquo;t hear about many civil engineers or corporate attorneys who do what they do because they enjoyed playing Zork on their dad&amp;rsquo;s office computer.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Symbolic Logic</title>
      <link>https://asthasr.github.io/posts/on-symbolic-logic/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2019 14:51:10 +0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://asthasr.github.io/posts/on-symbolic-logic/</guid>
      <description>I went to public school in the United States, and I was always &amp;ldquo;bad at math.&amp;rdquo; I hated homework and tests, and it never got better: as I went through the grades, the problems got longer and more intricate, and I inevitably would make a calculation error&amp;mdash;misplacing a decimal or flubbing an easy sum&amp;mdash;halfway through. I got used to seeing $\color{red}{-\frac{1}{2}}$ on my papers. Those add up!&#xA;In college, the first thing I did when planning my path through general education was look for a way to avoid Calculus.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Danger of &#34;Simplicity&#34;</title>
      <link>https://asthasr.github.io/posts/danger-of-simplicity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Nov 2019 09:05:35 +0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://asthasr.github.io/posts/danger-of-simplicity/</guid>
      <description>There are a few tendencies among programmers that involve the totem of &amp;ldquo;simplicity.&amp;rdquo; There&amp;rsquo;s the ancient concept of KISS, of course, but there&amp;rsquo;s also the much-abused YAGNI, the insistence that we &amp;ldquo;Choose Boring Technology,&amp;rdquo; entire languages that base their elevator pitch around the idea that they&amp;rsquo;re &amp;ldquo;simple,&amp;rdquo; and the concept in object-oriented design that &amp;ldquo;every class should have a single responsibility.&amp;rdquo;&#xA;The problem with these approaches is that &amp;ldquo;simplicity&amp;rdquo; never gets a rigorous definition.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Parsing&#34; in Python</title>
      <link>https://asthasr.github.io/posts/parsing-in-python/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2019 14:02:05 +0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://asthasr.github.io/posts/parsing-in-python/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently read &lt;a href=&#34;https://lexi-lambda.github.io/blog/2019/11/05/parse-don-t-validate/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Parse, Don&amp;rsquo;t Validate,&amp;rdquo;&#xA;&lt;/a&gt; shared it with my&#xA;coworkers, and let it &lt;a href=&#34;https://lobste.rs/s/uemphs/parse_don_t_validate&#34;&gt;bring me out of&#xA;retirement&lt;/a&gt; on&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lobste.rs/&#34;&gt;lobste.rs&lt;/a&gt;. It captures a concept that I&amp;rsquo;ve struggled to explain,&#xA;leading to cases where I couldn&amp;rsquo;t say why I thought something was better beyond a vague&#xA;&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s a matter of taste.&amp;rdquo; That&amp;rsquo;s not very satisfactory as a justification when you&amp;rsquo;re&#xA;trying to explain to someone why they should rework a piece of code in a review.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
